<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>ist402</title>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <subtitle>IST 402 course content space</subtitle>
  <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
  <author>
      <name></name>
  </author>
  <id>/feed</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Lab 4 - Webcomponents</title>
    <id>/labs/webcomponents-1</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T15:33:24-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</published>
    <summary>September 18th, 2019For this lab we're going to look at a few different services that are like codepen but allow for more advanced use-cases and development to support web components (and other front</summary>
    <link href="/labs/webcomponents-1"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <h3>September 18th, 2019</h3>
<p>For this lab we're going to look at a few different services that are like codepen but allow for more advanced use-cases and development to support web components (and other front end languages).</p>
<h3>Exercises</h3>
<p><b>Glitch.com</b>






 - A basic example of referencing and leveraging existing web components to do small things and insane things. Buttons, calendars, or... 3d model viewing???</p>
<ul><li><a href="https://glitch.com/~ui5-webcomponents">https://glitch.com/~ui5-webcomponents</a>






</li>






<li>
<a href="https://glitch.com/edit/#!/wcp-model-viewer?path=index.html:27:28">https://glitch.com/edit/#!/wcp-model-viewer?path=index.html:27:28</a>






<br/></li>






</ul>
<p><b>Stackblitz.com</b>






 - An example of three different web component libraries achieving the same result through similar syntax: 
<a href="https://stackblitz.com/edit/govsummit">https://stackblitz.com/edit/govsummit</a>






</p>
<p><b>Webcomponents.dev</b>






 - A Headless web application example: 
<a href="https://webcomponents.dev/edit/nBDd1nHi5clvN1QAdSys">https://webcomponents.dev/edit/nBDd1nHi5clvN1QAdSys</a>






</p>
<h3>How to submit to lab</h3>
<p>Similar to last week, we're going to fork and modify something but then we have a specific type of topic prompt for the response:</p>
<ol>
  <li><a href="https://webcomponents.dev/edit/KaQ3RE2hDjqwG48OPrnL">Fork this repo just like we did last week</a>



</li>




  <li>Update the details in <b>example-app</b>


 to relate to you</li>




  <li>Copy the <b>example-app</b>


 code and fill it out differently, demonstrating stacking / time savings</li>




  <li>update the CSS code to <b>remove the yellow background </b>



and<b> change the border color</b>



 of the css, impacting all copies (again, scale)</li>




  <li>Do your written response where it says "<i>Here's where you should fill in your response</i>


"</li>



<li>Pick <b>one of these </b>



to frame your writing and video response:	
    <ul>
    	<li>Make the <i>business</i>


, <i>security</i>


, <i>accessibility,</i>


 OR <i>design</i>



 case for using web components, leveraging links to support your case or through demonstration in one of the repos we've stepped through.</li>




      	<li><i>Code / Developer route</i>



: Run through <a href="https://lit-element.polymer-project.org/try">Try LitElement</a>



 and do a video explaining the value of LitElement, with supporting links.</li>



<li><i>Package manager / tooling pro</i>


: Setup NPM / node and create an element using Open-WC, the tooling the pros use <a href="https://open-wc.org/guide/">https://open-wc.org/guide/</a>


 and do a video on that process / making a hello-world element in it.</li>




    </ul>




  </li>




  <li>Record your video and link to it from your fork of the repo next to the writing area</li>


<li>Post in <b>#lab-4-webcomponents</b>



 in our slack group</li>


<li><a href="https://reclaimhosting.com">Purchase a domain / account on Reclaim hosting to prepare for next week</a>


</li>




</ol>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Webcomponents</title>
    <id>/topics/webcomponents</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T15:33:49-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</published>
    <summary>Slides - Web components & Package managersWeb components are the future of web development. Combined with package management systems like npm, they empower teams to leverage the work of others in a </summary>
    <link href="/topics/webcomponents"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Slides - <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/btopro/web-components-and-package-managers">Web components & Package managers</a>
</p>
<p>Web components are the future of web development. Combined with package management systems like npm, they empower teams to leverage the work of others in a sustainable, secure and accessible manner.</p>
<p>This week is mostly in slide form as a result of the many talks that btopro gives on these topics. This course is built out of web components and increasingly everything from signs at fast food restaurants to websites you use ever day (like YouTube) will be built out of web components.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>HTML / CSS / JS Web basics</title>
    <id>/topics/html-css-js-web-basics</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-09-09T16:53:00-04:00</published>
    <summary>Lecture Slides for Topic 3Load up the link machine. Many of these are inside the lecture presentation (in context)ResourcesCodePen.io - Great playground (where we'll do the lab today)Can</summary>
    <link href="/topics/html-css-js-web-basics"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://www.slideshare.net/btopro/html-css-js-web-basics">Lecture Slides for Topic 3</a>

</p>
<p>Load up the link machine. Many of these are inside the lecture presentation (in context)<br/></p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Resources</h3>
<ul><li><a href="https://codepen.io/">CodePen.io</a>



 - Great playground (where we'll do the lab today)</li>




<li><a href="https://caniuse.com/">CanIuse.com</a>



 - Determine browser compatibility with different CSS and JS capabilities</li>



<li><a href="https://getbootstrap.com/">https://getbootstrap.com/</a>



 - Bootstrap Design library, good for baseline styles and bringing responsive design (without thinking how)<br/></li>



<li><a href="https://fonts.google.com">Google Fonts</a>



 - Open source / easy to use CDN fonts</li>


<li><a href="https://gist.github.com/btopro/cf4ea532694b811324727d3f3be5fce7">For the glory of Old State bookmarklet</a>


</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/elmsln/lrnwebcomponents/blob/master/elements/hax-bookmarklet/README.md">HAX Bookmarklet</a>
</li>



</ul>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lab 3 - HTML / CSS / JS Web basics</title>
    <id>/labs/html-css-js-web-basics</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T15:32:58-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-09-09T16:53:00-04:00</published>
    <summary>September 11th, 2019For this lab we're going to be modifying three CodePens. The first one we'll do together in class for practice and getting a feel for HTML / CSS. JavaScript will come up again in </summary>
    <link href="/labs/html-css-js-web-basics"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <h3 class="hax-active">September 11th, 2019</h3>
<p>For this lab we're going to be modifying three CodePens. The first one we'll do together in class for practice and getting a feel for HTML / CSS. JavaScript will come up again in the future so we'll keep the JS brief for this one.</p>
<p><a href="https://codepen.io/btopro/pen/zYOWqKZ">Exercise Pen</a>

: <span style="font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Fork this Pen and we can follow along together in class.</span></p>
<h2>Lab Pen</h2>
<p>For this lab, I want you to modify <b>one of these</b>

 <b>pens</b>

 in order to make the resume reflect your own information. There's a <i>beginner Pen</i>

 and a more <i>advanced pen</i>

.</p>
<p><a href="https://codepen.io/btopro/pen/GRKQVBx?editors=1000">Beginner Pen</a>

: Personal Resume which contains hints and directions inside</p>
<p><a href="https://codepen.io/btopro/pen/GRKxKgX?editors=1000">Advanced Pen</a>

: no instructions and a slightly more advanced design. Use this to challenge yourself or if you've previously written HTML to make something more useful.</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Reflection Pen</h3>
<p><a href="https://codepen.io/btopro/pen/KKPozvd">FORK THIS PEN</a>

: For reflection this week I want you to fork this pen and write your response using HTML. For the topic this week pick one of the following:</p>
<ul><li>Explaining how to apply styling to an element in <b>CSS</b>

</li>

<li>Explain how to use JavaScript and <b>getElementById</b>

 to add a <i>click event to</i>

 an element in an existing codepen that generates an alert saying <b>Hello</b>

</li>

<li><i>Value of CodePen as a platform</i>

 to learn coding by finding an inspiring pen and explain what's going on.</li>

</ul>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Feedback</title>
    <id>/feedback</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-09-04T07:31:59-04:00</published>
    <summary>Lab 3When you include links, videos, images, etc in your video, try to copy and paste the link into the description on YouTube . This helps others explore the topics in greater detail AND DIRECTLY </summary>
    <link href="/feedback"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <h3><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Lab 3</span></h3>
<ul><li><span style="font-size: 24px; caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">When you include links, videos, images, etc in your video, try to copy and paste the link into the description on YouTube . This helps others explore the topics in greater detail<b> </b>
<i>AND DIRECTLY IMPROVES YOUR GOOGLE SEARCH RANKINGS OR SEO</i>

</span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: 24px; caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Speaking of SEO, checkout how Blake handled this 
<a href="https://codepen.io/blakeevanwills/pen/qBWYKqr" style="">https://codepen.io/blakeevanwills/pen/qBWYKqr</a>
</span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: 24px; caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><br/></span></li>

</ul>
<h3><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Lab 2</span></h3>
<ul><li>When you include links, videos, images, etc in your video, try to <b>copy and paste the link into the description on <i>YouTube</i>



</b>



. This helps others explore the topics in greater detail (general screen-caster tip)<br/></li>



<li>Frame topics in a vacuum, not in the context of our course. Act like this is a video you're making just to explain a topic to explain it. Next year someone might care about how to make a <b>Pull Request </b>



and learn from you, they won't know (or care) about IST 402 or that it's for school</li>



<ul><li><b>Job interview</b>



: I know how to do X, I can explain Y. Less <i>In class I learned about X, </i>



I did an <i>assignment once</i>



 about Y.</li>



</ul>




<li>Be mindful of time. It's hard (for me too) but the 2.5 to 5 minute target helps with engagement as well as helps you refine your words when speaking about topics fluidly</li>



<ul><li><b>Job interview</b>



: Be on point, precise in language, exacting in explanations and you demonstrate confidence in the topic matter.</li>



</ul>




<li>WRITE BEFORE SPEAKING. The blogging / writing aspect of the lab response is to help practice technical writing but also to frame your thoughts and find words that work for concepts.</li>



<ul><li>500 words == 5 minutes; 300, 3 minutes; these values are to help you get more exact in your language both written and verbal</li>



</ul>



<li><i>Walking and Chewing Gum is difficult</i>



 - You are not being judged on accuracy of things like "Did you issue the pull request perfectly that one time". Try to demonstrate the concept on video, live. Practice once beforehand if it helps smooth things out.</li>



<ul><li><b>Job interview</b>



: Thinking on the fly, not planned out canned responses to things. Fluid conversation mixing in and out of technical concepts isn't easy, that's why we're practicing it.</li>



</ul>



<li>To those treating this like a brand / identity, keep doing what your doing, many of these are flipping fantastic!</li>




</ul>
<h3>Lab 1</h3>
<ul><li>ABOB (made up acronym) - Always Be On Brand. Similar account names, same photos, interlink social accounts with writing with posts</li>






<li>Always leave 2-3 seconds on the front and back of a screencast</li>





<li>Do an audio levels check</li>





<li>Shoot for the same style sign on and sign off</li>





</ul>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Materials</title>
    <id>/materials</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-26T15:00:15-04:00</published>
    <summary>There are no required course materials in the textbook form but there are digital services you'll need to purchase for one of our Labs which will have usage in multiple labs in the future. These servi</summary>
    <link href="/materials"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>There are no required course materials in the textbook form but there are digital services you'll need to purchase for one of our Labs which will have usage in multiple labs in the future. These services are hosting from <a href="https://digitalocean.com">Digital Ocean</a>



 and a domain name from a registrar like <a href="https://hover.com/">Hover</a>



 or <a href="https://domains.google.com">Google Domains</a>



.</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Referral link</h3>
<p><a href="https://m.do.co/c/1fd5a3e0425d">ELMS:LN / HAXTheWeb referral link</a>


</p>
<p>If you use this referral link you should get at least 1 month free. <b>This is linked to an account the university uses</b>


 for people to get access to HAXcms and ELMS:LN demos in a safe, offsite location. This is also my way of saying that I don't benefit personally from you using Digital Ocean, I just like their simplicity.</p>
<p>These services were selected for price point and ease of use. We will be going through all the steps of setting up a new server on Digital Ocean (which involves clicking buttons basically) and then getting our custom domain name wired up to the Digital Ocean server.</p>
<p>There are $5/month plans on Digital Ocean and domain names can typically be purchased for $12.99/year though can run as low as $5 when on sale. After class is over it's up to you if you want to keep paying for hosting / keep your domain name active but expect to spend between <b>$25 and $50</b>
 depending on service you sign up for and domain name cost.</p>
<p>Paying more will get you access to faster server resources but are not required for what we're going to execute on the machine. <span style="font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">We will be setting up the server and talking about how to wire things up most likely as part of our 4th lab session of the semester.</span></p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Screencasting</title>
    <id>/resources/screencasting</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-26T14:27:20-04:00</published>
    <summary>ChecklistBefore recording always make sure...You've got the links you want to view open in tabs in a browser windowYou've got headphones / some kind of microphone to record your voiceYou can use i</summary>
    <link href="/resources/screencasting"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <h3 class="hax-active">Checklist</h3>
<p>Before recording always make sure...</p>
<ul><li>You've got the links you want to view open in tabs in a browser window</li>
<li>You've got headphones / some kind of microphone to record your voice</li>
<ul><li>You can use internal microphones but the quality on them is pretty bad so try to use a headset / earbuds if you have them</li>
</ul>

<li>You've authorized whatever it is to record your voice and test that audio is working!</li>
<ul><li>I fell victim to this many times early on</li>
</ul>
</ul>
<p>Next you'll need to pick a screen casting tool to do the recording. I recommend one of the following.</p>
<h3>Zoom (Free)</h3>
<p><b>Link</b>
: <a href="https://cmm.psu.edu/zoom/">https://cmm.psu.edu/zoom/</a>
</p>
<p>Penn state labs come with zoom installed. You can also install this on your personal device and should be able to do recordings from it. I recommend finding a quite place that you can bring headphones since you'll have to do voice over describing what's on screen and explaining it to others.</p>
<h3>Screencastify (Free, ad based with paid option)</h3>
<p><b>Link</b>
: <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/screencastify-screen-vide/mmeijimgabbpbgpdklnllpncmdofkcpn?hl=en">https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/screencastify-screen-vide/mmeijimgabbpbgpdklnllpncmdofkcpn?hl=en</a>
</p>
<p>I just found this recently, it's a browser plugin for Chrome. If <i>you're O.K. with the permissions that it requires</i>
, it's a very easy to use way of generating a screencast.</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Snagit (Paid)</h3>
<p><b>Link</b>
: 
<a href="https://www.techsmith.com/snagit-pricing.html">https://www.techsmith.com/snagit-pricing.html</a>
</p>
<p>I use Snagit personally for all of my screen casting that I do. It is $30 but comes with some basic ways of doing quick editing and image mock up as well. It's not required that you use Snagit by any means, just saying what I've had positive experiences with previously.</p>
<p>Others</p>
<p>If you find others that you like feel free to share them with the class. The purpose of this class is not to get into high end video editing so beware that it is expected you'll generate videos each week. The content of the video is what matters, not fancy intros or well cut jumps or anything like that. Being able to fluidly communicate about a technical concept and teach others about how to use it and what it is.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lab 2 - Git / Github / Contribution</title>
    <id>/labs/git</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-24T15:13:10-04:00</published>
    <summary>September 4th, 2019 - Lab 2We've talked about git for version control and explored Github a bit and how teams work together using the platform. Now let's dig in!Basic example / Getting startedCre</summary>
    <link href="/labs/git"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>
</p>
<h2>September 4th, 2019 - Lab 2</h2>
<p>We've talked about git for version control and explored Github a bit and how teams work together using the platform. Now let's dig in!</p>
<h3>Basic example / Getting started</h3>
<ol><li>Create a <a href="http://github.com/">GitHub account</a>












</li>













<li>Go to this repo off btopro's github account <a href="https://github.com/btopro/lab2/blob/master/README.md">by going to this link</a>







</li>










<li>Read along in the document and complete the tasks asked of you</li>











<li>We'll work through this in class and I'll mix between showing things interactively done between specific people as well as roaming around to answer questions</li>










<li>After you make the updates requested in the document, issue a "Pull Request" back against the source (my repo)</li>










<li>In the PR, fill out a brief overview of what you changed. This is the feedback loop typically found in modern web development!</li>












</ol>
<h3><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Let's start contributing to an open source project!</span></h3>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Let's start contributing to our first open source project! I've left a few issues in my own projects so that we can see the full project development life cycle at play here. I'm providing links below so your job is to fix one of these things and issue a pull request just like we did in the practice.</span></p>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">EVERYONE (me included) start out getting into a development community by updating documentation, making sure acronyms made sense and fixing links and typos. The best way to get into a software community is to fix things around the edges and ensure that you can effectively communicate with people in the project. It also helps prove they are human.</span></p>
<ol><li>Select one of the issues from this list of issues; Pick one from the number based on the row you are sitting in if still in class, if not, try to pick one that hasn't been closed yet or have comments on it.</li>






<ol><li>
HAXcms minor documentation clean up -<a href="https://github.com/elmsln/HAXcms/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3AHAXEdu">https://github.com/elmsln/HAXcms/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3AHAXEdu</a>






<br/>OR</li>






<li>HAXTheWeb minor documentation clean up - <a href="https://github.com/elmsln/haxtheweb.org/labels/HAXedu">https://github.com/elmsln/haxtheweb.org/labels/HAXedu</a>





<br/>OR</li>




<li>ELMS:LN minor documentation clean up - 
<a href="https://github.com/elmsln/elmsln/labels/HAXedu">https://github.com/elmsln/elmsln/labels/HAXedu</a>




<br/>OR</li>





<li>Add a <b>proper</b>

 description of the course to the <a href="https://github.com/btopro/ist402">https://github.com/btopro/ist402</a>





 README.md file and provide an issue describing the need to make the change<br/></li>






</ol>









<li>Read the description of what needs fixed, ask questions if you need clarification via commenting in the associated thread</li>










<li>Hit FORK on the repo (or go to your fork), fix the issue and submit a pull request.</li>









</ol>
<h3 class="hax-active"><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Writing / screencast / reflection lab submission</span></h3>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">For our reflection piece this week, pick one of the following topics (or multiple if you like)</span></p>
<ul><li><span style="letter-spacing: 0.5px;">Markdown<br/></span></li>







<li><span style="letter-spacing: 0.5px;">Git</span></li>







<li><span style="letter-spacing: 0.5px;">Pull Requests</span></li>







</ul>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">In your screencast talk about one of these four above as far as what it is and then showcase it in context of what we did in the lab. This could involve talking about what Pull Requests are while showing off a link that has good tutorials on Pull Request workflows, then showing the relevant links in the project you selected associated with a pull Request. <b>It could also be showing you talking about proposing changes to a file in a repo, then doing it in the UI and talking about what's happening.</b>







</span></p>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">I only bold that text because then you'd be saving time; doing the Lab while talking about doing the lab; which demonstrates you get the concept, while showing someone else how to accomplish the same task.</span></p>
<h3><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Submitting your reflection</span></h3>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">This week our blogging piece will take place in the fork of your github repo for Lab2. There's a boilerplate file I created called <b><i>lab2/blob/master/Reflection.md</i>







</b>







 which asks you to write your post there using some basic markdown for practice and linking to your video post.</span></p>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;" class="hax-active">Then when you've made your post in <b>github</b>







, post it into the <b>#</b>
</span><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;"><b>lab-2-git-github</b>
</span><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px; font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);"> channel in our ist-402 slack group.</span></p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lab 1 - Building your digital identity</title>
    <id>/labs/building-your-digital-identity</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</published>
    <summary>August 28th, 2019 - Lab 1 / first classThis is a warm up lab that will help set the stage for the platforms we'll use for the rest of the semester.Create a Slack account and join two slack channels</summary>
    <link href="/labs/building-your-digital-identity"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <h2>August 28th, 2019 - Lab 1 / first class</h2>
<p>This is a warm up lab that will help set the stage for the platforms we'll use for the rest of the semester.</p>
<ol><li>Create a Slack account and join two slack channels</li>











<ul><li><b style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">IST 402</b>











<span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);"> - <a href="https://join.slack.com/t/ist-402/shared_invite/enQtNzI5OTAyMTczNjY1LTUzZDQ1ZDFmMmU1ZTM1MTViN2QyNDAyNWJkYjgwZDhlYzc3ZDNhYTc1MjhhZWJhNjAyYjIxOGJlMWM2MGI3NGM">Slack Invite</a>








</span></li>











<ul><li>We'll use this as the primary working space / link sharing / communication space for the course</li>











</ul>











<li><b style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">ELMS: Learning Network - </b>








<span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);"><a href="https://join.slack.com/t/elmsln/shared_invite/enQtMjg2MzUxMTYyNjcyLWNhYzU1ODk0MjQ5MWZlNjVjNWJkMmZlODJiMGNmNDBjODk2NDc2MDUzNTZkODE4NTRiMjUzYzkzOTBkNjI4NGE">Slack Invite</a>








</span></li>











<ul><li>Me and my band of nuts are available to you. If you want to get more involved in this space beyond what we'll experience in class or have questions about the education or web industry, the door is always open</li>

<li>There's developers and educational professionals from multiple universities there, IST and otherwise.</li>











</ul>











</ul>












<li>Think up a brand / identity / persona for your online identity as an IT professional</li>











<ul><li>What does your brand feel like?</li>











<ul><li>Great Explainer? Hero's Journey? Future CIO?</li>











</ul>











<li>Pick a name that you can attempt to use across "all platforms"</li>











<ul><li>Domain name, Github, Twitter, LinkedIn, YouTube</li>











</ul>











<li>Note: You MAY want to divorce this from your real persona / personal accounts. Everyone does it differently in industry; many merge, there are risks associated with that. I fragment on YouTube  but generally keep all mine unified.<br/></li>

<li>Because we haven't started a blog yet (but let's get in the swing of doing a write up and a video), write up a paragraph describing your brand in Word/Docs</li>











</ul>











<li>Register this account on Github, Twitter, LinkedIn, YouTube</li>











<ul><li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Be sure to set the username to be the same across them</span></li>











</ul>











<li>Create a Playlist on YouTube called "Clarissa explains it all", replacing <span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Clarissa</span> with your persona</li>











<li>Create a screencast that's 3 - 5 minutes long that includes the following:</li>











<ul><li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Pick a screencasting solution <a href="resources/screencasting">from the Screencasting resources area</a>


</span></li>



<li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">introducing your channel <i><b>from a technology professional context</b>






</i>






</span></li>










<li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Showing your favorite tech blog / anything you've read and enjoy learning from online currently. Talk about an article on the blog while it's being shown in order to practice the explainer concept.</span></li>










<li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">End with what piece of technology you'd like to learn more about how it works from the topics in the survey</span></li>










</ul>










<li><span style="caret-color: rgb(25, 30, 35);">Post a link to this video on your social accounts (Twitter / LinkedIn) with some setup to try and draw people to it using 3 hashtags.</span></li>

<li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Use the </span><b style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">IST402 Slack directly</b>
<span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);"> and upload your Word/Doc file to the channel named </span><i style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text); font-weight: bold;">#lab-1-brand-management.</i>
<i style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);"> </i>
<span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Make sure to include a link to your YouTube Channel and Video post in the bottom of your "blog" post</span><br/></li>
<li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);"><b>Extra if you'd like</b>
</span></li>
<ol><li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">If you @btopro on twitter I'll RT to increase reach</span></li>
<li>@EdTechJoker is an account that will post into the "Socialmedia" channel in our slack channel. You're welcome to use this for social reach / to try it out as well</li>

</ol>




</ol>
<a11y-gif-player src="https://media3.giphy.com/media/iRMLJCZH4CA24/giphy.gif" src-without-animation="https://media1.giphy.com/media/iRMLJCZH4CA24/480w_s.jpg" alt="melissa joan hart clarissa darling hip checks word art in the 90s... wow the 90s were bad." schema-resource-id="#b2b41292-2a5a-b2de-a3b3" resource="#b2b41292-2a5a-b2de-a3b3" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " style="width: 75%;"></a11y-gif-player>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Labs</title>
    <id>/labs</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</published>
    <summary>We'll have a lab almost every week of the semester which we'll start in class and then will be yours to finish on your own time. Most labs should be able to be completed in 1-2 hours total.Remember t</summary>
    <link href="/labs"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>We'll have a lab almost every week of the semester which we'll start in class and then will be yours to finish on your own time. Most labs should be able to be completed in 1-2 hours total.</p>
<p><b>Remember that after each lab you have to do a concise overview of the topic in the form of a blog post and a YouTube explainer video, then submit it to Slack for review.</b>
</p>
<p>We'll start out class the following week reviewing some videos and posts created by the class to point out what worked well and what could have been done better in presenting the previous topic.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Goals.. for you!</title>
    <id>/goals-for-you-</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-21T15:11:14-04:00</published>
    <summary>My primary goal for you is to learn new things about modern web technologies while getting hands on with them. More specifically...Learning not just what a technology is but...Who's using it, what </summary>
    <link href="/goals-for-you-"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>My primary goal for you is to learn new things about modern web technologies while getting hands on with them. More specifically...</p>
<ul><li>Learning not just what a technology is but...</li>

<ul><li>Who's using it, what industries, what web services</li>

<li>Getting hands on and implementing it small scale</li>

<li>Being able to better communicate purpose and ideas around it</li>

</ul>


<li>Building a digital footprint of YOU, the IT worker / manager / developer / whatever your path, just that it's out there!</li>

<ul><li>Creating a YouTube channel of explainer videos about the topics discussed in class</li>

<li>Creating a Blog about these same topics</li>

<li>Creating social coder accounts and connecting them all together (like Github, TravisCI, Stackblitz, CodePen, Glitch, IFTTT, etc)</li>

</ul>

<li>Learn about all levels of "the stack" in order to better empathize with those working in different levels of the stack from you (or people you'll one day manage)</li>

<li>Have a website on the internet that you control and have a window into how all aspects of it function.</li>
<li><i>Take hand written tests</i>
 and <i>use platforms and technologies that no employer on earth will care about</i>
 once you graduate</li>

</ul>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Ok.. maybe not that last one but the rest are legit.</span></p>
<meme-maker alt="troll GIF" image-url="https://media3.giphy.com/media/eVy46EWyclTIA/giphy.gif" bottom-text="Ok, not that last one." imageurl="https://media3.giphy.com/media/eVy46EWyclTIA/giphy.gif" toptext="troll GIF" style="width: 75%;"></meme-maker>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>After class reflection</title>
    <id>/after-class-reflection</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-21T15:11:14-04:00</published>
    <summary>All assignments are setup as labs and you'll be starting into them at the end of class. Once finished with the lab, you'll demonstrate you've done the work by reflecting on it in the form of a written</summary>
    <link href="/after-class-reflection"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>All assignments are setup as labs and you'll be starting into them at the end of class. Once finished with the lab, <b>you'll demonstrate you've done the work by reflecting on it in the form of a written response as well as a video response. </b>
Then we'll review some of the responses at the start of the next class. <b>Scroll down to read both things that you are expected to complete each week as part of reflection on the topic of the lab. Yes I enjoy bold text.</b>

</p>
<h3>Written response</h3>
<p>To each technology, I'd like you to write a short blog post that reads like a one-page white paper about the technology at hand. Try to keep it to around 500 words but thoroughness is more important then "did I make the paper long enough".</p>
<p>As long as it answers questions like the following:</p>
<ul><li>What is it and why does it exist</li>

<li>What industries use it / who are players that popularize it?</li>

<li>What alternatives exist to it?</li>

<li>Links / Resources for people who want to learn more about it</li>

<li>What you struggled with in using it?</li>

<li>What you liked most about using it?</li>

</ul>
<h3><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;" class="hax-active">Video response</span></h3>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Explainer videos are great, especially for people on the go via podcasts or who are looking to get a refresher on a topic before a meeting. Make a 3-5 minute screencast that sets up what the topic is, and runs through some brief examples of it. This is open to interpretation but you are trying to explain to others why this topic is valuable and when they'd use it.</span></p>
<ul><li><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);" class="hax-active">Say quickly who you are</span></li>

<li><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Explain in 30 seconds what the topic is, who's using it or why it's useful</span></li>

<li><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Talk about the topic while showing a demo of it or place you found most useful to learn</span></li>

<li><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Show links to resources where you can learn more about it</span></li>

<li><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Awesome sign off phrase to remember you by</span></li>

</ul>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Here are a few examples of the kind of formality that is expected (flip on screencast software, record screen, talk). Part of the video reflection is to get more comfortable with speaking about technical concepts and to improve your ability to rationalize what your doing. I don't use a script (ever) for my videos but that's up to you.</span></p>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XDsuFrLWY5w&list=PLJQupiji7J5dqyIVrKfPOujZKuqbmgJKm&index=28&t=0s">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XDsuFrLWY5w&list=PLJQupiji7J5dqyIVrKfPOujZKuqbmgJKm&index=28&t=0s</a>

<br/></span></p>
<p>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q4e4Z32mITo&list=PLJQupiji7J5dqyIVrKfPOujZKuqbmgJKm&index=8&t=0s<br/></p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Class time together</title>
    <id>/class-time-together</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-21T15:04:55-04:00</published>
    <summary>We're going to strive for this general flow to each week of the semester. A few specific topics will deviate and we may have some guest speakers, but generally this is what class will look like togeth</summary>
    <link href="/class-time-together"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>We're going to strive for this general flow to each week of the semester. A few specific topics will deviate and we may have some guest speakers, but generally this is what class will look like together</p>
<ul><li>Capability / skill / technology of the day with quick discussion of what people think that's for, or places they've heard of it previously</li>

<li>A brief lecture (25 - 30 min) about the skill, who uses it, and how it's put into practice. This is taking the concept into the theory realm.</li>

<li>Screw theory, we're only going to learn by getting our hands dirty! We'll take a quick break to prep the keyboards. (10 min for questions, 5 min break)</li>

<li>Next we'll all follow along doing a very basic example of the skill / a warm up activity. This might be running commands in a terminal or hooking up a new IFTTT command to Github via the UI. Something that's all of us following along and doing it together, stopping to answer any questions along the way.</li>

<li>The rest of the time from here is open lab. We'll have a lab each week with a few options for experiencing and implementing the skill in practice.</li>

<li>What ever you don't get done in class is to be completed after class but we'll always start on the work together in case there are issues.</li>

</ul>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Project</title>
    <id>/project</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</published>
    <summary>The last week of the semester there will be a slightly longer lab that I'm calling a project. You'll have to put together a pitch for one of multiple problem spaces but it's a technical pitch. You'll </summary>
    <link href="/project"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>The last week of the semester there will be a slightly longer lab that I'm calling a project. You'll have to put together a pitch for one of multiple problem spaces but it's a technical pitch. You'll be asked to use as many technologies we used in the course to express how you'll solution will utilize these technologies, while it still being in the form of a pitch.</p>
<p>This will be explained more as we go into the course but it's effectively a double lab as far as points and time involved. There is no final exam so it's just a final project</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building your digital identity</title>
    <id>/topics/building-your-digital-identity</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T17:01:42-04:00</published>
    <summary>Slides from the talk in classNo one knows who you are if you're not effectively communicating. I recall a colleague several years ago getting pissed that I was invited to speak some place. "It's li</summary>
    <link href="/topics/building-your-digital-identity"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://www.slideshare.net/btopro/edtechjoker-ist-402-syllabus-day">Slides from the talk in class</a>

</p>
<p>No one knows who you are if you're not effectively communicating. I recall a colleague several years ago getting pissed that I was invited to speak some place. "It's like no one knows I exist or appreciates what I know". He was absolutely just as or more tallented than I was... what was the difference?</p>
<ul><li>I've blogged openly about tech and life since 2008</li>



<li>I've got hundreds of YouTube videos ranging from "Hey look at this thing" to "let's learn about..." to "We're going to burn down this space"</li>




<li>I've got unified social media accounts that signal boost content from the other spaces</li>



</ul>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">As a result of having a unified social media front and regular presence on blogs / YouTube, I've gotten to speak nationally on a regular basis the last ten years. <b>Every recorded association of a brand or event to you personally is another form of signal boosting.</b>



</span></p>
<h3 class="hax-active"><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Theory</span></h3>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">A theory I learned about in Grad school that stuck with me the most is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actor%E2%80%93network_theory">Actor Network Theory</a>



 (ANT). ANT can be argued as to if it's actually a theory, but the <b>TLDR;</b>



 is that all things influence each other.</span></p>
<a11y-gif-player src="https://media1.giphy.com/media/aVtdz7iNVPI1W/giphy.gif" src-without-animation="https://media2.giphy.com/media/aVtdz7iNVPI1W/480w_s.jpg" alt="full house animation of young daughter saying DUH and rolling eyes" schema-resource-id="#d7c9f858-a9be-b117-7795" resource="#d7c9f858-a9be-b117-7795" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " style="width: 25%;"></a11y-gif-player>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">For information sciences though, it's saying that anything created influences anything else created. This is particularly potent in the digital space when we can create a logo, brand, business, website, identity, or platform seemingly out of thin air. If I post on YouTube, I'm not just broadcasting there and increasing my brand recognition in that space. It's aggregated to blogs, it shows up in Google and Bing search results. Its lifted for replication on Russian botnet sites.</span></p>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">All of this, amplifies your voice and reach far beyond you speaking in public (again, duh). But if you recognize this, you can also weaponize it to your advantage (or be a Russian troll bot online and corrupt other countries cultures, I mean tomatoe tomatto). Through intentionality, we can increase our profile as technology professionals and begin to build a portfolio that anyone can stumble on (or seek out intentionally) to increase their knowledge.</span></p>
<p class="hax-active"></p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Questions driven teaching</title>
    <id>/question-driven-teaching</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T16:18:39-04:00</published>
    <summary>In all the technologies and skillsets we'll explore in this course, I want you to approach them with the same questions that I have explored in my career. These simple questions will help you decipher</summary>
    <link href="/question-driven-teaching"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>In all the technologies and skillsets we'll explore in this course, I want you to approach them with the same questions that I have explored in my career. These simple questions will help you decipher what's going to get you the furthest for the longest.</p>
<p>Technological sustainability is not easy; both in remaining relevant by sustaining your own skills as well as the sustained use of any solution by anyone or their organization.</p>
<p>What problem does this solve?</p>
<p>Who built this?</p>
<p>Where is this being used?</p>
<p>How can I go about using it?</p>
<p>Why do people use this over alternatives? (and what are the top 3 alternatives)</p>
<p>With each problem / solution space we look at in this course we're going to look at it through the lens of these questions.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Initial skills assessment</title>
    <id>/technologies-we-explore</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T16:17:19-04:00</published>
    <summary>It's not as scary as that title.We'll be exploring lots of different technologies through labs. In order to give me a good sense of what everyone's past experience is with these technologies, please </summary>
    <link href="/technologies-we-explore"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>It's not as scary as that title.</p>
<p>We'll be exploring lots of different technologies through labs. In order to give me a good sense of what everyone's past experience is with these technologies, please complete the very short anonymous skills survey.</p>
<p>You aren't judged on this or graded, it's just to help me know how best to pace the course so that we can make the best use of our time together.</p>
<html-block style="margin: 0px auto; display: block;">
<iframe src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLScCtAPX3fj1TXdNMyb1UgL83tex0z54Ya8JEG0N4zrzV8afCA/viewform?embedded=true" width="100%" height="1200" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0">Loading…</iframe>


</html-block>
<p><a href="https://forms.gle/BpRv39fV5jZFMLg77">Open the above survey in a new window</a>

</p>
<p>This is just to help me get a sense of things everyone has had past experience with so I know what to focus on in what order and in how much depth. These labs are designed to give you working knowledge of all of the things listed and to be able to have a conversation with managers, hiring groups, and developers about the tools IT organizations / start ups need to utilize on a daily basis.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Resources</title>
    <id>/resources</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>This list will keep growingGithub - Popular code sharing spaceSlack - Popular productivity hub / collaboration locationDigital Ocean - Easy to use server environmentHover / Google Domains</summary>
    <link href="/resources"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>This list will keep growing</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com">Github</a>

 - Popular code sharing space</p>
<p><a href="https://slack.com">Slack</a>

 - Popular productivity hub / collaboration location</p>
<p><a href="https://digitalocean.com">Digital Ocean </a>

- Easy to use server environment</p>
<p><a href="https://hover.com">Hover</a>

 / <a href="https://domains.google.com">Google Domains</a>

 - Easy to buy domain registrar</p>
<p><a href="https://elmsln.org/">ELMS:LN</a>

 - Penn State developed learning platform</p>
<p><a href="https://haxtheweb.org/">HAXcms</a>

 - Penn State developed flat file CMS (powers this course site)</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Topic overview</title>
    <id>/topics</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>ARE YOU READY!?Are you ready to hit power level 9000!? Then read through this lesson plan to be a super saiyan.Topic / semester outlineHere's the proposed topics I</summary>
    <link href="/topics"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <grid-plate layout="6/6" responsive-size="sm" style="width: 100%;"><h2 slot="col-1">ARE YOU READY!?</h2>











<p slot="col-1"><span style="font-size: 24px; letter-spacing: 0.5px; caret-color: rgb(25, 30, 35);">Are you ready to hit power level 9000!? Then read through this lesson plan to be a super saiyan.</span><br/></p>









<meme-maker slot="col-2" alt="dragon ball z GIF by Geek & Sundry" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/3ohrydqJVXULwIffIk/giphy.gif" bottom-text="Said no one... ever" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/3ohrydqJVXULwIffIk/giphy.gif" toptext="dragon ball z GIF by Geek & Sundry" style="width: 75%;"></meme-maker>












</grid-plate>
<h3 class="hax-active">Topic / semester outline</h3>
<p>Here's the proposed topics I've come up with to start. We may deviate from here as far as timing or how long we spend on different ones.</p>
<ul><li>Week 1 - Establishing an online identity as an
IT Professional (Vlogger)</li>






<ul><li>Treating ourselves as brands, we will establish
accounts and begin to setup the foundation for submission of assignments
throughout the semester</li>






</ul>






<li>Week 2 – Git / Github / Contribution (All roles)</li>






<ul><li>Collaborative participation on Github,
understanding concepts of Git / version control and how teams leverage this
technology for code and <b style="font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">non-code
projects</b>




</li>




</ul>




<ul>

</ul>






<li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Week 3 - HTML / CSS / JavaScript & the web (Front end)</span></li>






<ul><li>The big three powering most of what you use
today, a primer for reverse engineering. We’ll use codepen to demonstrate how
you can extend concepts of github into other realms</li>
</ul>






<li>Week 4 - Web components & Package management & Progressive Web
Apps (Front end)</li>






<ul><li>HTML on steroids and the future of all
application development, web or otherwise</li>






<li>We’ll look at why this is transformative for
application development and why all teams should be exploring it from an
efficiency perspective. We’ll also experiment with a powerful new platform
called Stackblitz to demonstrate the power of Package management +
compartmentalized HTML</li>
<li>NPM / Composer and how we stand on the shoulders of giants</li>
</ul>
<li>Week 5 - Reclaim Hosting & CPanel & GravCMS</li>
<ul><li>We're going to dig into <a href="https://reclaimhosting.com/"><b>Reclaim</b>
 <b>hosting</b>
</a>
 for the next several lessons and to give us a server to deploy CMSs on. CMSs come in different shapes and sizes and this will kick off several weeks looking at different CMSs in depth</li>
<li><b>Reclaim</b>
 uses <a href="https://cpanel.net/">CPanel</a>
 - A hosting management platform which makes installing new applications a click away. We'll explore the CPanel interface and open the door to installing and experimenting with many different applications.</li>
<li>We'll use GravCMS as our first vehicle into CPanels powers. GravCMS is a powerful yet simple static file driven website. It's built in PHP yet reads off <b>Markdown</b>
 files in order to generate content. We'll explore the GravCMS user interface, learn why people use it and look at some sites built using it.</li>
</ul>
<li>Week 6 - <a href="https://drupal.org/">Drupal CMS</a>
</li>
<ul><li>We'll look at the Drupal community, it's history, structure and learn about why it's popular at a high level</li>
<li>We'll dig into the Drupal UI and look at the more powerful aspects of it as to why people put up for lack of UX in exchange for raw power like User / role management and entity / field management</li>
<li>We'll setup a basic Drupal site in <b>Reclaim</b>
 <b>hosting</b>
 to explore the guts of our own real working Drupal site.</li>
</ul>
<li>Week 7 - <a href="https://wordpress.org/">WordPress CMS</a>
</li>
<ul><li>We'll look at the WordPress community and platform as it is the worlds most used open source CMS, thought to power some 30+% of all websites</li>
<li>We'll dig into the WordPress UI, look at the Gutenberg editor, and see why more people build smaller websites using WordPress than any other platform out there today</li>
<li>We'll setup a basic WordPress site in <b>Reclaim</b>
 <b>hosting</b>
 to explore the guts of our own real working WordPress site.</li>
</ul>
<ul>



</ul>




<ul>

</ul>






<li><b style="font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Week 8 – Mid-term</b>






</li>






<ul><li>We’ll have a mid-term based on the technologies and skills covered the 1<sup style="letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text); font-weight: bold;">st</sup>






<span style="font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text); font-weight: bold;">
 half</span></li>






<li><b style="font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">There will be no lab this week.</b>






</li>






<li><span style="font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Come to class, take the exam and then you're free to leave or use the open lab time for catching up on past labs.</span></li>






</ul>






<li>Week 9 - Open source communities & <a href="https://github.com/elmsln/haxcms">HAXcms</a>
 (All roles)</li>






<ul><li>We’ll review governance within open source
communities, understand the difference between licenses, learn how different structures operate (including Open vs Closed), see how to identify
healthy vs stagnated open source communities, and learn when people fallback to proprietary technologies. ELMS:LN / HAXcms had to go through a formal audit from the <a href="https://apereo.org/">Apereo Foundation</a>
, so I'll provide insight into what got us certified as a well formed software community.</li>




<li>We'll try to identify gaps in on boarding into a community and help improve the documentation associated with this by installing and experimenting with HAXcms, a system I've dubbed an <b>organic static site generator</b>
.</li>
</ul>
<li>Week 10 – Servers, Terminal and Command line basics and DDOS (Sys admin)<br/></li>
<ul>
<li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Step by step through the basic commands that system developers use to make everything work</span><br/></li>
<li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Looking at </span><a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/" style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Cloudflare</a>
<span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">
 and discussing Denial of Service attacks</span><br/></li>
</ul>
<ul>


<li>We'll play with https://surge.sh/ for static publishing</li>






</ul>






<li>Week 11 – Accessibility (Front end / Developer)</li>






<ul><li>What is it, why is it important, who benefits,
how do we test for it?</li>
<li>We'll use Lighthouse and Wave to test different websites and parse through the reports</li>
<li>We'll also have a guest speaker from the university who works in disability services, Sonya Woods, to talk about accessibility and her job as a specialist in this field.</li>






</ul>






<li>Week 12 - User experience (Front end / Designer)</li>






<ul><li>Persona creation and testing using real world
applications</li>






</ul>






<li>Week 13 - Server Virtualization technologies (DevOps)</li>






<ul><li>Vagrant and Docker have changed the web forever,
we’ll explore these and surrounding applications and learn why they are so
powerful</li>






</ul>






<li><b style="font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Week 14 –
Thanksgiving Break</b>






</li>






<ul><li><b style="font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Eat items.</b>






</li>






</ul>






<li>Week 15-16 Educational Technology, Open
Education Resources (Edtech)</li>






<ul><li>We’ll look at the courses we’re taking and its
usage of technology, where this technology is usable, where it’s not. Where
accessibility can be improved or accounted for.</li>






<li>We’ll look at OER / open course technology
movements from philosophical, societal and technological perspectives.</li>






<li>We’ll audit systems the instructor works on /
has worked on to identify gaps in existing technologies, critique what’s
available and ideate about how technologies discussed throughout the class can
be leveraged</li>






<li><b>These labs will be combined into a single submission with 10% of the grade. Lab time will be spent learning about the context and having access to instructors to help while exploring the topic.</b>






</li>






</ul>






</ul>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>About the instructor (boring)</title>
    <id>/welcome/welcome/about-the-instructor</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>This is the approved, boring version of who I am. If you found this page, bring it up in class and you'll be rewarded with a crisp high five.My name is Bryan Ollendyke and I've been living workin</summary>
    <link href="/welcome/welcome/about-the-instructor"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>This is the approved, boring version of who I am. If you found this page, bring it up in class and you'll be rewarded with a crisp high five.</p>
<a11y-gif-player src="https://media3.giphy.com/media/5wWf7GW1AzV6pF3MaVW/giphy.gif" src-without-animation="https://media0.giphy.com/media/5wWf7GW1AzV6pF3MaVW/480w_s.jpg" alt="high five the office" schema-resource-id="#0e8a5bdc-121d-e719-bbe6" resource="#0e8a5bdc-121d-e719-bbe6" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " style="width: 100%;"></a11y-gif-player>
<p>My name is Bryan Ollendyke and I've been <strike>living</strike>


 working at Penn State since 2007. I did my undergrad in IST and was able to get a job working in the College of Arts & Architecture's online learning unit (now called Office of Digital Learning).</p>
<p>In 2015 I completed my MS by studying the spread of an open source platform called Drupal. The theory I reasoned from my thesis is an effect I call Information Altruism -- Meaning that it isn't open source software that impacts institutions <b>but the free giving away of knowledge about how to use it</b>


 which does.</p>
<p>Open source lays the ground work, but it still requires knowledge workers to pick up those raw minerals and make rails of them for organizations to ride on.</p>
<p>I am in the rare position of getting to teach you leveraging tools which I and my team have built. This content is written in a platform called HAXcms which we are actively building. I'm also the project lead on a project called ELMS: Learning Network.</p>
<p>Since starting at Penn State, I would say 99.5% of every hour of every day I work is contributed directly back to open code and documentation. I've contributed hundreds of modules for Drupal, dozens of themes and installation profiles, millions of lines of code liberated from the ownership of anyone or anywhere.</p>
<p>In the last two years, our team has released north of 400 reusable design assets called Web components. These modules and design assets power thousands of websites and help empower people we'll never know to better express themselves online, whether for instructional content or otherwise.</p>
<p>I'm a self described Developer Activist in that I don't think open source can change society: I know it can and does constantly. It's why I still work in academia - to try and open source as much of the application stack associated with teaching and learning in order to provide both better options as well as lower costs.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Syllabus</title>
    <id>/syllabus</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>A standard syllabus is a contract between us.IST 402 Fall 2019 Syllabus (PDF) / (Docx format)</summary>
    <link href="/syllabus"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>A standard syllabus is a contract between us.</p>
<p><a href="https://psu.box.com/s/2dp0l2ex01d4nz9ovxcg9f8jnkupsr0j">IST 402 Fall 2019 Syllabus (PDF)</a>
 / (<a href="https://psu.box.com/s/2feisa6840l8h0mb5uvhw1nl9tce2hzb">Docx format</a>
)</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Git / Github / Contribution</title>
    <id>/topics/git</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>Link to the slides from class.Git is a free and open source distributed version control system designed to handle everything from small to very large projects with speed and efficiency.Git provide</summary>
    <link href="/topics/git"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://www.slideshare.net/btopro/background-info-on-git-github">Link to the slides from class</a>
.</p>
<lrndesign-blockquote citation="git-scm.com" source-link="https://git-scm.com/" display-mode="default" resource="#8b61e53c-8efa-f160-e9f8" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " style="width: 100%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;"><span>Git is a free and open source distributed version control system designed to handle everything from small to very large projects with speed and efficiency.</span>
</lrndesign-blockquote>
<p>Git provides a command line interface or CLI that allows developers to track changes in the code they are writing. Some basic commands in git are as follows</p>
<code-sample copy-clipboard-button>  <template preserve-content="preserve-content"># create a new repo
git init

# create a file
touch Readme.md

# add file to git
git add -A

# "commit" the change
git commit -m "Initial readme created"

# "push" the change to a repository
git push origin master</template>
</code-sample>
<p>All git is doing, is keeping track of a simple record that indicates what a line number WAS and what it should be now. Here's an example from the HAXcms Readme file</p>
<img src="files/2019-08-24_15-21-52.png" alt="Looking at a git commit diff to see what something became" style="width: 100%;"/><p>In this example, we can see that lines 18 and 19 in the file called README.md were changed. The left in red is what it was. The right in green is what it became. This visualization is provided by Github, where I manage the vast majority of my projects.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/">Github</a>

 is a popular space for developers in and out of open source software communities to collaborate. Microsoft recently purchased Github but the platform has been popular with developers of open source projects for over a decade prior.</p>
<p>Github has gained popularity in part because</p>
<ul><li>Git as a version control system has largely won the popularity contest</li>

<li>They allow you to use the platform for free so long as what you do is open source</li>

<li>Private repos then allow companies to align their open contribution strategy with their internal development workflows</li>


<li>Github's social networking aspects around issue queues, following, forking and staring repos have all helped improve the social aspect of software development online</li>

<li><i>Github is adding capabilities to make code contributions without needing to understand everything that goes into making the contribution. </i>

Capabilities like clicking edit on the website, making a change in the browser and typing the commit name, then it automatically saving the change or creating a "Pull Request" for whoever owns the file</li>

<li>All of these reasons are why developers <b>and non-developers</b>

 are joining Github to do a lot of open source contribution.</li>

<li>Lots of other services and "apps" are starting to integrate with Github as a platform and as a login system</li>

</ul>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">There is an open source variation of GitHub called GitLab. Gitlab is used by the university to share code internally (like WebAccess, security related code), automate workflows and increase collaboration between organizations.</span></p>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">For the purposes of this class we're going to focus on Github as it will provide the most visibility for you and what you are showcasing as being able to do.</span></p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome</title>
    <id>/welcome</id>
    <updated>2019-09-18T14:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:46:06-04:00</published>
    <summary>IST 402: Emerging TechnologiesRepo backing this websiteMy name is Bryan Ollendyke, and welcome to IST 402: Emerging Tech!I'm excited to expose you to the ideas and technologies I wish I h</summary>
    <link href="/welcome"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <h2>IST 402: Emerging Technologies</h2>
<p><a href="https://github.com/btopro/ist402">Repo backing this website</a>
</p>
<grid-plate layout="8/4" responsive-size="md" style="width: 100%;"><p slot="col-1">My name is Bryan Ollendyke, and welcome to IST 402: Emerging Tech!</p>









<p slot="col-1">I'm excited to expose you to the ideas and technologies I wish I had been exposed to when I was in IST. I graduated from IST in 2006 (and again in 2015), and while I took some programming focused courses in undergrad, it wasn't until I starting working on projects for the university that I had to learn on the job all aspects of real software development.</p>

<p slot="col-1"><br/></p>



<p slot="col-1">I am a unicorn in the industry. A unicorn is often known as a "Full Stack Developer". It's a thing that "doesn't exist" or isn't to be sought after. The market tends to force hyper specialization, front end, back end, sys ops, dev ops, css / designer as opposed to one person that can touch all aspects of the application. I've been collecting a mix of unicorns through my work at the university and would love to share our experiences with you and expose you to technologies we work on every day.</p>





<p slot="col-1">I love open source software, hockey, web technologies, Penn State, and meme's.... cause obviously. I present regularly at events around the country on web components, educational technology, NGDLE, and Drupal / PHP at both technical events and educator centric ones.</p>



<p slot="col-1">I walk between worlds and hope to provide you with a unique perspective in the process!</p>









<meme-maker image-url="files/headshot.jpg" top-text="Your" bottom-text="Professor" imageurl="files/headshot.jpg" slot="col-2" style="width: 75%;"></meme-maker>




<meme-maker style="width: 75%;" image-url="files/headshot.jpg" top-text="is so" bottom-text="strange" imageurl="files/headshot.jpg" slot="col-2"></meme-maker>









</grid-plate>
<h2>Course description</h2>
<p>We're going to learn about and participate in open source software communities. We're going to use github to do this. We're going to make YouTube channels full of knowledge that you've assembled in this course, create social media posts promoting it and other projects you'll work on, and generally give you a sense of the skills required to get involved in start up culture.</p>
<p>We'll cover human things like workflow management, user experience, community building and accessibility.</p>
<p>We'll get into amazing web services like Stackblitz.io, CloudFlare, DigitalOcean, Github, IFTTT, TravisCI, Slack, talk about how they work, play with them, and blog about using them.</p>
<p>We'll cover technical concepts like Web components, version control (git), Content managment systems, "flat file" systems.</p>
<p>We'll get hands on and write markdown, yaml, json, web components (HTML/CSS/JS).</p>
<p>We'll "build servers" and make our own website to understand how all that works.</p>
<p>We'll generally remove the magic that divides consumers from producers in the digital realm and get you a step closer being involved in a start up.</p>
<p>The vast majority of your work will be done out in the open to help you build an identity as an IT professional and someone that has the right accounts and is active with them come interview time or where ever you find yourself after this place.</p>
<p>My goals for this course are to get you more comfortable with these tools, build your online personal / brand, and hopefully get you commits to real world open source projects.</p>
<grid-plate layout="4/4/4" responsive-size="md">


<meme-maker alt="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" bottom-text="Are" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" toptext="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" slot="col-1"></meme-maker>






<meme-maker alt="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" bottom-text="Ready?" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" toptext="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" slot="col-3" top-text=""></meme-maker>






<meme-maker alt="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" bottom-text="You" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" toptext="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" slot="col-2"></meme-maker>






</grid-plate>
<h2>(Boring) "Blue Book" description from {<i>terrible</i>


} LionPath</h2>
<h3>Start up? Let's Tool up!</h3>
<p>The "Start up" culture is a world that lives by "move fast and break things". But how do you get into the start up scene? Or more importantly, what do you need to know in order to attract offers, and get your resume to stand out in a world where thousands of "IT workers" will graduate along side you.</p>
<p>You'll contribute to a large Penn State lead Open Source software project while building your digital identity as an IT professional on your journey to 1337 (elite). You'll improve online education while using things like version control (git), docker, web components, terminal, servers, screencasting and writing technical documentation.</p>
<p>You'll work with platforms like Github, Digital Ocean, HAXcms, IFTTT, Slack, Travis CI and YouTube. Prior programming knowledge is beneficial but understanding of technical concepts is more important.</p>
<p>(Fun) Reality description</p>
<p>This</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>