<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>ist402</title>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <subtitle>IST 402 course content space</subtitle>
  <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
  <author>
      <name></name>
  </author>
  <id>/feed</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Lab 1 - Building your digital identity</title>
    <id>/labs/blank</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T10:57:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</published>
    <summary>August 28th, 2019 - Lab 1 / first classThis is a warm up lab that will help set the stage for the platforms we'll use for the rest of the semester.Create a Slack account and join two slack channels</summary>
    <link href="/labs/blank"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <h2>August 28th, 2019 - Lab 1 / first class</h2>
<p>This is a warm up lab that will help set the stage for the platforms we'll use for the rest of the semester.</p>
<ol><li>Create a Slack account and join two slack channels</li>
<ul><li><b style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">IST 402</b>
<span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);"> - </span><a href="https://join.slack.com/t/ist-402/shared_invite/enQtNzI5OTAyMTczNjY1LTUzZDQ1ZDFmMmU1ZTM1MTViN2QyNDAyNWJkYjgwZDhlYzc3ZDNhYTc1MjhhZWJhNjAyYjIxOGJlMWM2MGI3NGM" style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">https://join.slack.com/t/ist-402/shared_invite/enQtNzI5OTAyMTczNjY1LTUzZDQ1ZDFmMmU1ZTM1MTViN2QyNDAyNWJkYjgwZDhlYzc3ZDNhYTc1MjhhZWJhNjAyYjIxOGJlMWM2MGI3NGM</a>
</li>
<ul><li>We'll use this as the primary working space / link sharing / communication space for the course</li>
</ul>
<li><b style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">ELMS: Learning Network </b>
<span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">- </span><a href="https://join.slack.com/t/elmsln/shared_invite/enQtMjg2MzUxMTYyNjcyLWNhYzU1ODk0MjQ5MWZlNjVjNWJkMmZlODJiMGNmNDBjODk2NDc2MDUzNTZkODE4NTRiMjUzYzkzOTBkNjI4NGE" style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">https://join.slack.com/t/elmsln/shared_invite/enQtMjg2MzUxMTYyNjcyLWNhYzU1ODk0MjQ5MWZlNjVjNWJkMmZlODJiMGNmNDBjODk2NDc2MDUzNTZkODE4NTRiMjUzYzkzOTBkNjI4NGE</a>
</li>
<ul><li>Me and my band of nuts are available to you. If you want to get more involved in this space beyond what we'll experience in class, the door is always open</li>
</ul>
</ul>

<li>Think up a brand / identity / persona for your online identity as an IT professional</li>
<ul><li>What does your brand feel like?</li>
<ul><li>Great Explainer? Hero's Journey? Future CIO?</li>
</ul>
<li>Pick a name that you can attempt to use across "all platforms"</li>
<ul><li>Domain name, Github, Twitter, LinkedIn, YouTube</li>
</ul>
<li>Note: You MAY want to divorce this from your real persona / personal accounts. Everyone does it differently in industry; many merge, there are risks associated with that. I fragment on YouTube  but generally keep all mine unified.<br/></li>
</ul>
<li>Register this account on github, twitter, linkedIn, YouTube</li>
<ul><li><span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Be sure to set the username to be the same across them</span></li>
</ul>
<li>Create a Playlist on YouTube called {screen name} " explains"</li>
<li>Create a screencast that's 2 - 5 minutes long that includes the following:</li>
<ol><li>introducing your channel and showing a link to your favorite </li>
</ol>
</ol>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Labs</title>
    <id>/labs</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/labs"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Goals.. for you!</title>
    <id>/goals-for-you-</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-21T15:11:14-04:00</published>
    <summary>My primary goal for you is to learn new things about modern web technologies while getting hands on with them. More specifically...Learning not just what a technology is but...Who's using it, what </summary>
    <link href="/goals-for-you-"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>My primary goal for you is to learn new things about modern web technologies while getting hands on with them. More specifically...</p>
<ul><li>Learning not just what a technology is but...</li>

<ul><li>Who's using it, what industries, what web services</li>

<li>Getting hands on and implementing it small scale</li>

<li>Being able to better communicate purpose and ideas around it</li>

</ul>


<li>Building a digital footprint of YOU, the IT worker / manager / developer / whatever your path, just that it's out there!</li>

<ul><li>Creating a YouTube channel of explainer videos about the topics discussed in class</li>

<li>Creating a Blog about these same topics</li>

<li>Creating social coder accounts and connecting them all together (like Github, TravisCI, Stackblitz, CodePen, Glitch, IFTTT, etc)</li>

</ul>

<li>Learn about all levels of "the stack" in order to better empathize with those working in different levels of the stack from you (or people you'll one day manage)</li>

<li>Have a website on the internet that you control and have a window into how all aspects of it function.</li>
<li><i>Take hand written tests</i>
 and <i>use platforms and technologies that no employer on earth will care about</i>
 once you graduate</li>

</ul>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Ok.. maybe not that last one but the rest are legit.</span></p>
<meme-maker alt="troll GIF" image-url="https://media3.giphy.com/media/eVy46EWyclTIA/giphy.gif" bottom-text="Ok, not that last one." imageurl="https://media3.giphy.com/media/eVy46EWyclTIA/giphy.gif" toptext="troll GIF" style="width: 75%;"></meme-maker>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>After class reflection</title>
    <id>/after-class-reflection</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-21T15:11:14-04:00</published>
    <summary>All assignments are setup as labs and you'll be starting into them at the end of class. Once finished with the lab, you'll demonstrate you've done the work by reflecting on it in the form of a written</summary>
    <link href="/after-class-reflection"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>All assignments are setup as labs and you'll be starting into them at the end of class. Once finished with the lab, <b>you'll demonstrate you've done the work by reflecting on it in the form of a written response as well as a video response. Scroll down to read both. Yes I enjoy bold text.</b>
</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Written response</h3>
<p>To each technology, I'd like you to write a short blog post that reads like a one-page white paper about the technology at hand. Try to keep it to around 500 words but thoroughness is more important then "did I make the paper long enough".</p>
<p>As long as it answers questions like the following:</p>
<ul><li>What is it and why does it exist</li>
<li>What industries use it / who are players that popularize it?</li>
<li>What alternatives exist to it?</li>
<li>Links / Resources for people who want to learn more about it</li>
<li>What you struggled with in using it?</li>
<li>What you liked most about using it?</li>
</ul>
<h3><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;" class="hax-active">Video response</span></h3>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Explainer videos are great, especially for people on the go via podcasts or who are looking to get a refresher on a topic before a meeting. Make a 3-5 minute screencast that sets up what the topic is, and runs through some brief examples of it. This is open to interpretation but you are trying to explain to others why this topic is valuable and when they'd use it.</span></p>
<ul><li><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);" class="hax-active">Say quickly who you are</span></li>
<li><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Explain in 30 seconds what the topic is, who's using it or why it's useful</span></li>
<li><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Talk about the topic while showing a demo of it or place you found most useful to learn</span></li>
<li><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Show links to resources where you can learn more about it</span></li>
<li><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Awesome sign off phrase to remember you by</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Here are a few examples of the kind of formality that is expected (flip on screencast software, record screen, talk). Part of the video reflection is to get more comfortable with speaking about technical concepts and to improve your ability to rationalize what your doing. I don't use a script (ever) for my videos but that's up to you.</span></p>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XDsuFrLWY5w&list=PLJQupiji7J5dqyIVrKfPOujZKuqbmgJKm&index=28&t=0s">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XDsuFrLWY5w&list=PLJQupiji7J5dqyIVrKfPOujZKuqbmgJKm&index=28&t=0s</a>
<br/></span></p>
<p>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q4e4Z32mITo&list=PLJQupiji7J5dqyIVrKfPOujZKuqbmgJKm&index=8&t=0s<br/></p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Class time together</title>
    <id>/class-time-together</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-21T15:04:55-04:00</published>
    <summary>We&#39;re going to strive for this general flow to each week of the semester. A few specific topics will deviate and we may have some guest speakers, but generally this is what class will look like togeth</summary>
    <link href="/class-time-together"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>We're going to strive for this general flow to each week of the semester. A few specific topics will deviate and we may have some guest speakers, but generally this is what class will look like together</p>
<ul><li>Capability / skill / technology of the day with quick discussion of what people think that's for, or places they've heard of it previously</li>
<li>A brief lecture (25 - 30 min) about the skill, who uses it, and how it's put into practice. This is taking the concept into the theory realm.</li>
<li>Screw theory, we're only going to learn by getting our hands dirty! We'll take a quick break to prep the keyboards. (10 min for questions, 5 min break)</li>
<li>Next we'll all follow along doing a very basic example of the skill. This might be running commands in a terminal or hooking up a new IFTTT command to Github via the UI. Something that's all of us following along and doing it together, stopping to answer any questions along the way.</li>
<li>The rest of the time from here is open lab. We'll have a lab with a few options for experiencing and implementing the skill in practice.</li>
<li>What ever you don't get done in class is to be completed after class but we'll always start on the work together in case there are issues.</li>
</ul>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Responsive / Mobile design</title>
    <id>/topics/responsive-/-mobile-design</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/responsive-/-mobile-design"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Project</title>
    <id>/project</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</published>
    <summary>The last week of the semester there will be a slightly longer lab that I'm calling a project. You'll have to put together a pitch for one of multiple problem spaces but it's a technical pitch. You'll </summary>
    <link href="/project"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>The last week of the semester there will be a slightly longer lab that I'm calling a project. You'll have to put together a pitch for one of multiple problem spaces but it's a technical pitch. You'll be asked to use as many technologies we used in the course to express how you'll solution will utilize these technologies, while it still being in the form of a pitch.</p>
<p>This will be explained more as we go into the course but it's effectively a double lab as far as points and time involved. There is no final exam so it's just a final project</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Web components / HTML</title>
    <id>/topics/web-components-/-html</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T17:01:42-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/web-components-/-html"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building your digital identity</title>
    <id>/topics/building-your-digital-identity</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T17:01:42-04:00</published>
    <summary>No one knows who you are if you're not effectively communicating. I recall a colleague several years ago getting pissed that I was invited to speak some place. "It's like no one knows I exist or appre</summary>
    <link href="/topics/building-your-digital-identity"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>No one knows who you are if you're not effectively communicating. I recall a colleague several years ago getting pissed that I was invited to speak some place. "It's like no one knows I exist or appreciates what I know". He was absolutely just as or more tallented than I was... what was the difference?</p>
<ul><li>I've blogged openly about tech and life since 2008</li>
<li>I've got hundreds of YouTube videos ranging from "Hey look at this thing" to "let's learn about..." to "We're going to burn down this space"</li>

<li>I've got unified social media accounts that signal boost content from the other spaces</li>
</ul>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">As a result of having a unified social media front and regular presence on blogs / YouTube, I've gotten to speak nationally on a regular basis the last ten years. <b>Every recorded association of a brand or event to you personally is another form of signal boosting.</b>
</span></p>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">Theory</span></p>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">A theory I learned about in Grad school that stuck with me the most is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actor%E2%80%93network_theory">Actor Network Theory</a>
 (ANT). ANT can be argued as to if it's actually a theory, but the <b>TLDR;</b>
 is that all things influence each other.</span></p>
<a11y-gif-player src="https://media1.giphy.com/media/aVtdz7iNVPI1W/giphy.gif" src-without-animation="https://media2.giphy.com/media/aVtdz7iNVPI1W/480w_s.jpg" alt="full house animation of young daughter saying DUH and rolling eyes" schema-resource-id="#d7c9f858-a9be-b117-7795" resource="#d7c9f858-a9be-b117-7795" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " style="width: 25%;"></a11y-gif-player>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">For information sciences though, it's saying that anything created influences anything else created. This is particularly potent in the digital space when we can create a logo, brand, business, website, identity, or platform seemingly out of thin air. If I post on YouTube, I'm not just broadcasting there and increasing my brand recognition in that space. It's aggregated to blogs, it shows up in Google and Bing search results. Its lifted for replication on Russian botnet sites.</span></p>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px;">All of this, amplifies your voice and reach far beyond you speaking in public (again, duh). But if you recognize this, you can also weaponize it to your advantage (or be a Russian troll bot online and corrupt other countries cultures, I mean tomatoe tomatto). Through intentionality, we can increase our profile as technology professionals and begin to build a portfolio that anyone can stumble on (or seek out intentionally) to increase their knowledge.</span></p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Open source software Communities</title>
    <id>/topics/open-source-software</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T17:01:42-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/open-source-software"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>User experience</title>
    <id>/topics/user-experience</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T17:01:42-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/user-experience"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Questions driven teaching</title>
    <id>/question-driven-teaching</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T16:18:39-04:00</published>
    <summary>In all the technologies and skillsets we'll explore in this course, I want you to approach them with the same questions that I have explored in my career. These simple questions will help you decipher</summary>
    <link href="/question-driven-teaching"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>In all the technologies and skillsets we'll explore in this course, I want you to approach them with the same questions that I have explored in my career. These simple questions will help you decipher what's going to get you the furthest for the longest.</p>
<p>Technological sustainability is not easy; both in remaining relevant by sustaining your own skills as well as the sustained use of any solution by anyone or their organization.</p>
<p>What problem does this solve?</p>
<p>Who built this?</p>
<p>Where is this being used?</p>
<p>How can I go about using it?</p>
<p>Why do people use this over alternatives? (and what are the top 3 alternatives)</p>
<p>With each problem / solution space we look at in this course we're going to look at it through the lens of these questions.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Initial skills assessment</title>
    <id>/technologies-we-explore</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T16:17:19-04:00</published>
    <summary>It's not as scary as that title.We'll be exploring lots of different technologies through labs. In order to give me a good sense of what everyone's past experience is with these technologies, please </summary>
    <link href="/technologies-we-explore"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>It's not as scary as that title.</p>
<p>We'll be exploring lots of different technologies through labs. In order to give me a good sense of what everyone's past experience is with these technologies, please complete the very short anonymous skills survey.</p>
<p>You aren't judged on this or graded, it's just to help me know how best to pace the course so that we can make the best use of our time together.</p>
<html-block style="margin: 0px auto; display: block;">
<iframe src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLScCtAPX3fj1TXdNMyb1UgL83tex0z54Ya8JEG0N4zrzV8afCA/viewform?embedded=true" width="100%" height="1200" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0">Loading…</iframe>


</html-block>
<p><a href="https://forms.gle/BpRv39fV5jZFMLg77">Open the above survey in a new window</a>

</p>
<p>This is just to help me get a sense of things everyone has had past experience with so I know what to focus on in what order and in how much depth. These labs are designed to give you working knowledge of all of the things listed and to be able to have a conversation with managers, hiring groups, and developers about the tools IT organizations / start ups need to utilize on a daily basis.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Automation / Docker / IFTTT</title>
    <id>/topics/docker</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/docker"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Topic overview</title>
    <id>/topics</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:55-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>ARE YOU READY!?Are you ready to hit power level 9000!? Then read through these lessons.But seriously. We&#39;re going to work through these different topics to skill up and get a better feel f</summary>
    <link href="/topics"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <grid-plate layout="6/6" responsive-size="xl" style="width: 100%;"><h2 slot="col-1">ARE YOU READY!?</h2>



<p slot="col-1"><span style="font-size: 24px; letter-spacing: 0.5px; caret-color: rgb(25, 30, 35);">Are you ready to hit power level 9000!? Then read through these lessons.</span><br/></p>

<meme-maker slot="col-2" alt="dragon ball z GIF by Geek & Sundry" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/3ohrydqJVXULwIffIk/giphy.gif" bottom-text="Said no one... ever" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/3ohrydqJVXULwIffIk/giphy.gif" toptext="dragon ball z GIF by Geek & Sundry" style="width: 75%;"></meme-maker>




</grid-plate>
<p>But seriously. We're going to work through these different topics to skill up and get a better feel for the industry and how to participate in it.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Resources</title>
    <id>/resources</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>This list will keep growingGithub - Popular code sharing spaceSlack - Popular productivity hub / collaboration locationDigital Ocean - Easy to use server environmentHover / Google Domains - E</summary>
    <link href="/resources"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>This list will keep growing</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com">Github</a>
 - Popular code sharing space</p>
<p><a href="https://slack.com">Slack</a>
 - Popular productivity hub / collaboration location</p>
<p><a href="https://digitalocean.com">Digital Ocean </a>
- Easy to use server environment</p>
<p><a href="https://hover.com">Hover</a>
 / <a href="https://domains.google.com">Google Domains</a>
 - Easy to buy domain registrar</p>
<p><a href="https://elmsln.org/">ELMS:LN</a>
 - Penn State developed learning platform</p>
<p><a href="https://haxtheweb.org/">HAXcms</a>
 - Penn State developed flat file CMS (powers this website)</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Accessibility</title>
    <id>/topics/accessibility</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/accessibility"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>About the instructor (boring)</title>
    <id>/welcome/welcome/about-the-instructor</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>This is the approved, boring version of who I am. If you found this page, bring it up in class and you'll be rewarded with a crisp high five.My name is Bryan Ollendyke and I've been living workin</summary>
    <link href="/welcome/welcome/about-the-instructor"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>This is the approved, boring version of who I am. If you found this page, bring it up in class and you'll be rewarded with a crisp high five.</p>
<a11y-gif-player src="https://media3.giphy.com/media/5wWf7GW1AzV6pF3MaVW/giphy.gif" src-without-animation="https://media0.giphy.com/media/5wWf7GW1AzV6pF3MaVW/480w_s.jpg" alt="high five the office" schema-resource-id="#0e8a5bdc-121d-e719-bbe6" resource="#0e8a5bdc-121d-e719-bbe6" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " style="width: 100%;"></a11y-gif-player>
<p>My name is Bryan Ollendyke and I've been <strike>living</strike>


 working at Penn State since 2007. I did my undergrad in IST and was able to get a job working in the College of Arts & Architecture's online learning unit (now called Office of Digital Learning).</p>
<p>In 2015 I completed my MS by studying the spread of an open source platform called Drupal. The theory I reasoned from my thesis is an effect I call Information Altruism -- Meaning that it isn't open source software that impacts institutions <b>but the free giving away of knowledge about how to use it</b>


 which does.</p>
<p>Open source lays the ground work, but it still requires knowledge workers to pick up those raw minerals and make rails of them for organizations to ride on.</p>
<p>I am in the rare position of getting to teach you leveraging tools which I and my team have built. This content is written in a platform called HAXcms which we are actively building. I'm also the project lead on a project called ELMS: Learning Network.</p>
<p>Since starting at Penn State, I would say 99.5% of every hour of every day I work is contributed directly back to open code and documentation. I've contributed hundreds of modules for Drupal, dozens of themes and installation profiles, millions of lines of code liberated from the ownership of anyone or anywhere.</p>
<p>In the last two years, our team has released north of 400 reusable design assets called Web components. These modules and design assets power thousands of websites and help empower people we'll never know to better express themselves online, whether for instructional content or otherwise.</p>
<p>I'm a self described Developer Activist in that I don't think open source can change society: I know it can and does constantly. It's why I still work in academia - to try and open source as much of the application stack associated with teaching and learning in order to provide both better options as well as lower costs.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Git / Github / Contribution</title>
    <id>/topics/git</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/git"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Syllabus</title>
    <id>/syllabus</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>A standard syllabus is a contract between us (literally). You will receive a standard syllabus on the first day of class and it will be attached to this page for future reference.</summary>
    <link href="/syllabus"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>A standard syllabus is a contract between us (literally). You will receive a standard syllabus on the first day of class and it will be attached to this page for future reference.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome</title>
    <id>/welcome</id>
    <updated>2019-08-23T09:52:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:46:06-04:00</published>
    <summary>IST 402: Emerging TechnologiesMy name is Bryan Ollendyke, and welcome to IST 402: Emerging Tech!I'm excited to expose you to the ideas and technologies I wish I had been exposed to when I was</summary>
    <link href="/welcome"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <h2>IST 402: Emerging Technologies</h2>
<grid-plate layout="8/4" responsive-size="md" style="width: 100%;"><p slot="col-1">My name is Bryan Ollendyke, and welcome to IST 402: Emerging Tech!</p>







<p slot="col-1">I'm excited to expose you to the ideas and technologies I wish I had been exposed to when I was in IST. I graduated from IST in 2006 (and again in 2015), and while I took some programming focused courses in undergrad, it wasn't until I starting working on projects for the university that I had to learn on the job all aspects of real software development.</p>

<p slot="col-1">I am a unicorn in the industry. A unicorn is often known as a "Full Stack Developer". It's a thing that "doesn't exist" or isn't to be sought after. The market tends to force hyper specialization, front end, back end, sys ops, dev ops, css / designer as opposed to one person that can touch all aspects of the application. I've been collecting a mix of unicorns through my work at the university and would love to share our experiences with you and expose you to technologies we work on every day.</p>



<p slot="col-1">I love open source software, hockey, web technologies, Penn State, and meme's.... cause obviously. I present regularly at events around the country on web components, educational technology, NGDLE, and Drupal / PHP at both technical events and educator centric ones.</p>

<p slot="col-1">I walk between worlds and hope to provide you with a unique perspective in the process!</p>







<meme-maker image-url="files/headshot.jpg" top-text="Your" bottom-text="Professor" imageurl="files/headshot.jpg" slot="col-2" style="width: 75%;"></meme-maker>


<meme-maker style="width: 75%;" image-url="files/headshot.jpg" top-text="is so" bottom-text="strange" imageurl="files/headshot.jpg" slot="col-2"></meme-maker>







</grid-plate>
<h2>Course description</h2>
<p>We're going to learn about and participate in open source software communities. We're going to use github to do this. We're going to make YouTube channels full of knowledge that you've assembled in this course, create social media posts promoting it and other projects you'll work on, and generally give you a sense of the skills required to get involved in start up culture.</p>
<p>We'll cover human things like workflow management, user experience, community building and accessibility.</p>
<p>We'll get into amazing web services like Stackblitz.io, CloudFlare, DigitalOcean, Github, IFTTT, TravisCI, Slack, talk about how they work, play with them, and blog about using them.</p>
<p>We'll cover technical concepts like Web components, version control (git), Content managment systems, "flat file" systems.</p>
<p>We'll get hands on and write markdown, yaml, json, web components (HTML/CSS/JS).</p>
<p>We'll "build servers" and make our own website to understand how all that works.</p>
<p>We'll generally remove the magic that divides consumers from producers in the digital realm and get you a step closer being involved in a start up.</p>
<p>The vast majority of your work will be done out in the open to help you build an identity as an IT professional and someone that has the right accounts and is active with them come interview time or where ever you find yourself after this place.</p>
<p>My goals for this course are to get you more comfortable with these tools, build your online personal / brand, and hopefully get you commits to real world open source projects.</p>
<grid-plate layout="4/4/4" responsive-size="md">


<meme-maker alt="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" bottom-text="Are" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" toptext="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" slot="col-1"></meme-maker>




<meme-maker alt="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" bottom-text="Ready?" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" toptext="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" slot="col-3" top-text=""></meme-maker>




<meme-maker alt="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" bottom-text="You" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" toptext="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" slot="col-2"></meme-maker>




</grid-plate>
<h2>(Boring) "Blue Book" description from {<i>terrible</i>
} LionPath</h2>
<h3>Start up? Let's Tool up!</h3>
<p>The "Start up" culture is a world that lives by "move fast and break things". But how do you get into the start up scene? Or more importantly, what do you need to know in order to attract offers, and get your resume to stand out in a world where thousands of "IT workers" will graduate along side you.</p>
<p>You'll contribute to a large Penn State lead Open Source software project while building your digital identity as an IT professional on your journey to 1337 (elite). You'll improve online education while using things like version control (git), docker, web components, terminal, servers, screencasting and writing technical documentation.</p>
<p>You'll work with platforms like Github, Digital Ocean, HAXcms, IFTTT, Slack, Travis CI and YouTube. Prior programming knowledge is beneficial but understanding of technical concepts is more important.</p>
<p>(Fun) Reality description</p>
<p>This</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>