<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>ist402</title>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <subtitle>IST 402 course content space</subtitle>
  <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
  <author>
      <name></name>
  </author>
  <id>/feed</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Project</title>
    <id>/project</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/project"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Responsive / Mobile design</title>
    <id>/topics/responsive-/-mobile-design</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/responsive-/-mobile-design"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building your digital identity</title>
    <id>/topics/building-your-digital-identity</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T17:01:42-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/building-your-digital-identity"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Open source software Communities</title>
    <id>/topics/open-source-software</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T17:01:42-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/open-source-software"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Web components / HTML</title>
    <id>/topics/web-components-/-html</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T17:01:42-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/web-components-/-html"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>User experience</title>
    <id>/topics/user-experience</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T17:01:42-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/user-experience"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Question driven teaching</title>
    <id>/question-driven-teaching</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T16:18:39-04:00</published>
    <summary>In all the technologies and skillsets we'll explore in this course, I want you to approach them with the same questions that I have explored in my career. These simple questions will help you decipher</summary>
    <link href="/question-driven-teaching"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>In all the technologies and skillsets we'll explore in this course, I want you to approach them with the same questions that I have explored in my career. These simple questions will help you decipher what's going to get you the furthest for the longest.</p>
<p>Technological sustainability is not easy; both in remaining relevant by sustaining your own skills as well as the sustained use of any solution by anyone or their organization.</p>
<p>What problem does this solve?</p>
<p>Who built this?</p>
<p>Where is this being used?</p>
<p>How can I go about using it?</p>
<p>Why do people use this over alternatives? (and what are the top 3 alternatives)</p>
<p>With each problem / solution space we look at in this course we're going to look at it through the lens of these questions.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Technologies we explore</title>
    <id>/technologies-we-explore</id>
    <updated>2019-08-19T13:38:31-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T16:17:19-04:00</published>
    <summary>We'll be exploring lots of different technologies through labs. In order to give me a good sense of what everyone's past experience is with these technologies, please complete the very short anonymous</summary>
    <link href="/technologies-we-explore"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>We'll be exploring lots of different technologies through labs. In order to give me a good sense of what everyone's past experience is with these technologies, please complete the very short anonymous skills survey.</p>
<html-block style="margin: 0px auto; display: block;">
<iframe src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLScCtAPX3fj1TXdNMyb1UgL83tex0z54Ya8JEG0N4zrzV8afCA/viewform?embedded=true" width="100%" height="1200" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0">Loading…</iframe>

</html-block>
<p><a href="https://forms.gle/BpRv39fV5jZFMLg77">Open the above survey in a new window</a>
</p>
<p>This is just to help me get a sense of things everyone has had past experience with so I know what to focus on in what order and in how much depth. These labs are designed to give you working knowledge of all of the things listed and to be able to have a conversation with managers, hiring groups, and developers about the tools IT organizations / start ups need to utilize on a daily basis.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>About the instructor (boring)</title>
    <id>/welcome/welcome/about-the-instructor</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>This is the approved, boring version of who I am. If you found this page, bring it up in class and you'll be rewarded with a crisp high five.My name is Bryan Ollendyke and I've been living workin</summary>
    <link href="/welcome/welcome/about-the-instructor"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>This is the approved, boring version of who I am. If you found this page, bring it up in class and you'll be rewarded with a crisp high five.</p>
<a11y-gif-player src="https://media3.giphy.com/media/5wWf7GW1AzV6pF3MaVW/giphy.gif" src-without-animation="https://media0.giphy.com/media/5wWf7GW1AzV6pF3MaVW/480w_s.jpg" alt="high five the office" schema-resource-id="#0e8a5bdc-121d-e719-bbe6" resource="#0e8a5bdc-121d-e719-bbe6" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " style="width: 100%;"></a11y-gif-player>
<p>My name is Bryan Ollendyke and I've been <strike>living</strike>


 working at Penn State since 2007. I did my undergrad in IST and was able to get a job working in the College of Arts & Architecture's online learning unit (now called Office of Digital Learning).</p>
<p>In 2015 I completed my MS by studying the spread of an open source platform called Drupal. The theory I reasoned from my thesis is an effect I call Information Altruism -- Meaning that it isn't open source software that impacts institutions <b>but the free giving away of knowledge about how to use it</b>


 which does.</p>
<p>Open source lays the ground work, but it still requires knowledge workers to pick up those raw minerals and make rails of them for organizations to ride on.</p>
<p>I am in the rare position of getting to teach you leveraging tools which I and my team have built. This content is written in a platform called HAXcms which we are actively building. I'm also the project lead on a project called ELMS: Learning Network.</p>
<p>Since starting at Penn State, I would say 99.5% of every hour of every day I work is contributed directly back to open code and documentation. I've contributed hundreds of modules for Drupal, dozens of themes and installation profiles, millions of lines of code liberated from the ownership of anyone or anywhere.</p>
<p>In the last two years, our team has released north of 400 reusable design assets called Web components. These modules and design assets power thousands of websites and help empower people we'll never know to better express themselves online, whether for instructional content or otherwise.</p>
<p>I'm a self described Developer Activist in that I don't think open source can change society: I know it can and does constantly. It's why I still work in academia - to try and open source as much of the application stack associated with teaching and learning in order to provide both better options as well as lower costs.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Syllabus</title>
    <id>/syllabus</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>A standard looking syllabus but yet, a contract between us (literally).</summary>
    <link href="/syllabus"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>A standard looking syllabus but yet, a contract between us (literally).</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Git / Github / Contribution</title>
    <id>/topics/git</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/git"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Accessibility</title>
    <id>/topics/accessibility</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/accessibility"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Let's do this!</title>
    <id>/topics</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>ARE YOU READY!?Are you ready to hit power level 9000!? Then read through these lessons.But seriously. We're going to work through these different topics to skill up and get a better feel f</summary>
    <link href="/topics"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <grid-plate layout="6/6" responsive-size="xl" style="width: 100%;"><h2 slot="col-1">ARE YOU READY!?</h2>



<p slot="col-1"><span style="font-size: 24px; letter-spacing: 0.5px; caret-color: rgb(25, 30, 35);">Are you ready to hit power level 9000!? Then read through these lessons.</span><br/></p>

<meme-maker slot="col-2" alt="dragon ball z GIF by Geek & Sundry" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/3ohrydqJVXULwIffIk/giphy.gif" bottom-text="Said no one... ever" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/3ohrydqJVXULwIffIk/giphy.gif" toptext="dragon ball z GIF by Geek & Sundry" style="width: 75%;"></meme-maker>




</grid-plate>
<p>But seriously. We're going to work through these different topics to skill up and get a better feel for the industry and how to participate in it.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Automation / Docker / IFTTT</title>
    <id>/topics/docker</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary></summary>
    <link href="/topics/docker"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Resources</title>
    <id>/resources</id>
    <updated>2019-08-16T11:09:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:48:47-04:00</published>
    <summary>This list will keep growingGithub - Popular code sharing spaceSlack - Popular productivity hub / collaboration locationDigital Ocean - Easy to use server environmentHover / Google Domains - E</summary>
    <link href="/resources"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>This list will keep growing</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com">Github</a>
 - Popular code sharing space</p>
<p><a href="https://slack.com">Slack</a>
 - Popular productivity hub / collaboration location</p>
<p><a href="https://digitalocean.com">Digital Ocean </a>
- Easy to use server environment</p>
<p><a href="https://hover.com">Hover</a>
 / <a href="https://domains.google.com">Google Domains</a>
 - Easy to buy domain registrar</p>
<p><a href="https://elmsln.org/">ELMS:LN</a>
 - Penn State developed learning platform</p>
<p><a href="https://haxtheweb.org/">HAXcms</a>
 - Penn State developed flat file CMS (powers this website)</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome</title>
    <id>/welcome</id>
    <updated>2019-08-21T15:01:43-04:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-15T15:46:06-04:00</published>
    <summary>IST 402: Emerging TechnologiesMy name is Bryan Ollendyke, and welcome to IST 402: Emerging Tech!I'm excited to expose you to the ideas and technologies I wish I had been exposed to when I was</summary>
    <link href="/welcome"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <h2>IST 402: Emerging Technologies</h2>
<grid-plate layout="8/4" responsive-size="md" style="width: 100%;"><p slot="col-1">My name is Bryan Ollendyke, and welcome to IST 402: Emerging Tech!</p>







<p slot="col-1">I'm excited to expose you to the ideas and technologies I wish I had been exposed to when I was in IST. I graduated from IST in 2006 (and again in 2015), and while I took some programming focused courses in undergrad, it wasn't until I starting working on projects for the university that I had to learn on the job all aspects of real software development.</p>

<p slot="col-1">I am a unicorn in the industry. A unicorn is often known as a "Full Stack Developer". It's a thing that "doesn't exist" or isn't to be sought after. The market tends to force hyper specialization, front end, back end, sys ops, dev ops, css / designer as opposed to one person that can touch all aspects of the application. I've been collecting a mix of unicorns through my work at the university and would love to share our experiences with you and expose you to technologies we work on every day.</p>



<p slot="col-1">I love open source software, hockey, web technologies, Penn State, and meme's.... cause obviously. I present regularly at events around the country on web components, educational technology, NGDLE, and Drupal / PHP at both technical events and educator centric ones.</p>

<p slot="col-1">I walk between worlds and hope to provide you with a unique perspective in the process!</p>







<meme-maker image-url="files/headshot.jpg" top-text="Your" bottom-text="Professor" imageurl="files/headshot.jpg" slot="col-2" style="width: 75%;"></meme-maker>


<meme-maker style="width: 75%;" image-url="files/headshot.jpg" top-text="is so" bottom-text="strange" imageurl="files/headshot.jpg" slot="col-2"></meme-maker>







</grid-plate>
<h2>Course description</h2>
<p>We're going to learn about and participate in open source software communities. We're going to use github to do this. We're going to make YouTube channels full of knowledge that you've assembled in this course, create social media posts promoting it and other projects you'll work on, and generally give you a sense of the skills required to get involved in start up culture.</p>
<p>We'll cover human things like workflow management, user experience, community building and accessibility.</p>
<p>We'll get into amazing web services like Stackblitz.io, CloudFlare, DigitalOcean, Github, IFTTT, TravisCI, Slack, talk about how they work, play with them, and blog about using them.</p>
<p>We'll cover technical concepts like Web components, version control (git), Content managment systems, "flat file" systems.</p>
<p>We'll get hands on and write markdown, yaml, json, web components (HTML/CSS/JS).</p>
<p>We'll "build servers" and make our own website to understand how all that works.</p>
<p>We'll generally remove the magic that divides consumers from producers in the digital realm and get you a step closer being involved in a start up.</p>
<p>The vast majority of your work will be done out in the open to help you build an identity as an IT professional and someone that has the right accounts and is active with them come interview time or where ever you find yourself after this place.</p>
<p>My goals for this course are to get you more comfortable with these tools, build your online personal / brand, and hopefully get you commits to real world open source projects.</p>
<grid-plate layout="4/4/4" responsive-size="md">


<meme-maker alt="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" bottom-text="Are" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" toptext="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" slot="col-1"></meme-maker>




<meme-maker alt="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" bottom-text="Ready?" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" toptext="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" slot="col-3" top-text=""></meme-maker>




<meme-maker alt="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" image-url="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" bottom-text="You" imageurl="https://media0.giphy.com/media/nDSlfqf0gn5g4/giphy.gif" toptext="happy dance GIF by SpongeBob SquarePants" slot="col-2"></meme-maker>




</grid-plate>
<h2>(Boring) "Blue Book" description from {<i>terrible</i>
} LionPath</h2>
<h3>Start up? Let's Tool up!</h3>
<p>The "Start up" culture is a world that lives by "move fast and break things". But how do you get into the start up scene? Or more importantly, what do you need to know in order to attract offers, and get your resume to stand out in a world where thousands of "IT workers" will graduate along side you.</p>
<p>You'll contribute to a large Penn State lead Open Source software project while building your digital identity as an IT professional on your journey to 1337 (elite). You'll improve online education while using things like version control (git), docker, web components, terminal, servers, screencasting and writing technical documentation.</p>
<p>You'll work with platforms like Github, Digital Ocean, HAXcms, IFTTT, Slack, Travis CI and YouTube. Prior programming knowledge is beneficial but understanding of technical concepts is more important.</p>
<p>(Fun) Reality description</p>
<p>This</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>