<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>ist402</title>
    <link>/rss.xml</link>
    <description>IST 402 course content space</description>
    <copyright>Copyright (C) 2019 </copyright>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 16:33:19 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Question driven teaching</title>
      <link>/question-driven-teaching</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>In all the technologies and skillsets we'll explore in this course, I want you to approach them with the same questions that I have explored in my career. These simple questions will help you decipher what's going to get you the furthest for the longest.</p>
<p>Technological sustainability is not easy; both in remaining relevant by sustaining your own skills as well as the sustained use of any solution by anyone or their organization.</p>
<p>What problem does this solve?</p>
<p>Who built this?</p>
<p>Where is this being used?</p>
<p>How can I go about using it?</p>
<p>Why do people use this over alternatives? (and what are the top 3 alternatives)</p>
<p>With each problem / solution space we look at in this course we're going to look at it through the lens of these questions.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/question-driven-teaching</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 16:18:39 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building your digital identity</title>
      <link>/getting-started/building-your-digital-identity</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/getting-started/building-your-digital-identity</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 16:17:19 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Technologies we explore</title>
      <link>/technologies-we-explore</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>While touching on many, here is a list of technologies we'll be exploring throughout the course. These tools are not used by every organization out there, but huge swaths of the start up scene will have these or solutions like them.</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">Git / Github / Version control</h2>
<p>Quickly becoming the developer account portal to the start up universe, Github is both code management platform and project management platform. It can be used for open source software (which made it so popular) but also paid plans allow for private repos.</p>
<p>Socially, many use github data (commits, stars, discussions, pull requests) to demonstrate effectiveness in communities. We'll use github to give you the following skills:</p>
<ul><li>Make an account if you don't already have one</li>
<li>Learn the terms of the trade and what Github is a UI on top of</li>
<li>Learn how to do Pull Requests</li>
<li>Learn</li>
</ul>
<p><span style="letter-spacing: -0.48px; caret-color: rgb(25, 30, 35);"><br/></span></p>
<p><br/></p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/technologies-we-explore</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 16:17:19 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Policies</title>
      <link>/syllabus/policies</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h4>University Policies</h4>
<ol><li><b>Disability / alternate media:</b>

<br/>If you have a documented disability, send a copy of the letter from the Office of Disability services to your instructor (using Canvas email). If you suspect that you have a disability but have not been assessed, you must contact the Office of Disability Services at <a href="http://equity.psu.edu/ods/applying-for-services-from-ods">http://equity.psu.edu/ods/applying-for-services-from-ods</a>

<br/> </li>

<li><strong>PSU Counseling And Psychological Services (CAPS):</strong>

<br/>Penn State’s Counseling and Psychological Services (CAPS) offers its students mental health services in the form of case management, community resource referrals, supportive listening, care giver support and much more. Services are designed to enhance students' ability to fully benefit from the University environment and academic experience. Call CAPS at 814-863-0395 (8 am-5 pm, Monday-Friday EST) or submit an inquiry online at <a href="http://studentaffairs.psu.edu/counseling/contact_form.shtml" target="_blank">http://studentaffairs.psu.edu/counseling/contact_form.shtml</a>

 to schedule an appointment. The mental health advocate can help you address mental health concerns that may interfere with your academic progress or social development. Common concerns include anxiety, depression, relationship difficulties and stress.If you or someone you know is experiencing a crisis situation please call your local crisis center or 911.<br/> </li>

<li><strong>Student Misconduct:</strong>

<br/>Clearly, both the online and the face-to-face learning world present similar chances for inappropriate student behaviors. All expectations and policies regarding student conduct are ultimately guided by Penn State’s Code of Conduct (<a href="http://studentaffairs.psu.edu/conduct/codeofconduct/">http://studentaffairs.psu.edu/conduct/codeofconduct/</a>

). In brief, the University’s Code of Conduct states that all students should act with personal integrity, respect other students’ dignity, rights and property, and help create and maintain an environment in which all can succeed through the fruits of their efforts. Any student behaving in a manner which violates these essential principles will be subject to disciplinary sanctions.<br/> </li>

<li><strong>Plagiarism/academic integrity:</strong>

<br/>Academic integrity — the pursuit of scholarly activity in an open, honest and responsible manner, free of fraud and deception — is an important educational objective of Penn State. Academic integrity is a basic guiding principle for all academic activity at The Pennsylvania State University, and all members of the University community are expected to act in accordance with this principle.<br/><br/>Academic dishonesty can lead to a failing grade or referral to the<a href="https://studentaffairs.psu.edu/conduct/Procedures.shtml"> Office of Student Conduct</a>

.<br/><br/>Academic dishonesty includes, but is not limited to:<br/>- cheating<br/>- plagiarism<br/>- fabrication of information or citations<br/>- facilitating acts of academic dishonesty by others<br/>- unauthorized prior possession of examinations<br/>- submitting the work of another person or work previously used without informing the instructor and securing written approval​<br/>- tampering with the academic work of other students<br/> </li>

<li><strong>University Policy AD 40</strong>

<br/>All course materials students receive or to which students have online access are protected by copyright laws. Students may use course materials and make copies for their own use as needed, but <strong>unauthorized distribution and/or uploading of materials without the instructor’s express permission is strictly prohibited. </strong>

 Students who engage in the unauthorized distribution of copyrighted materials may be held in violation of the University’s Code of Conduct, and/or liable under Federal and State laws. University Policy AD 40, the University Policy Recording of Classroom Activities and Note Taking Services addresses this issue more specifically: <a href="https://guru.psu.edu/policies/AD40.html">https://guru.psu.edu/policies/AD40.html</a>

<br/><br/><strong>Course Policies</strong>

<br/> </li>

<li><strong>Inappropriate Assistance</strong>

<br/>We expect that students will complete course assignments without inappropriate assistance from other individuals. We assume that all work submitted for a grade will be solely the product of the student’s own understanding of the course subject material and completed without inappropriate conceptual or technical assistance from another person. In this course, “inappropriate assistance” would involve the solicitation of another individual to complete a review or quiz for you, in part or in full. <strong>Any instance of inappropriate assistance in the submission of academic work will be considered a violation of the Academic Integrity policy.</strong>

<br/> </li>

</ol>
<p></p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabus/policies</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:58:42 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About the instructor</title>
      <link>/welcome/welcome/about-the-instructor</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>My name is Bryan Ollendyke and I've been <strike>living</strike>
 working at Penn State since 2007. I did my undergrad in IST and was able to get a job working in the College of Arts & Architecture's online learning unit (now called Office of Digital Learning).</p>
<p>In 2015 I completed my MS by studying the spread of an open source platform called Drupal. The theory I reasoned from my thesis is an effect I call Information Altruism -- Meaning that it isn't open source software that impacts institutions <b>but the free giving away of knowledge about how to use it</b>
 which does.</p>
<p>Open source lays the ground work, but it still requires knowledge workers to pick up those raw minerals and make rails of them for organizations to ride on.</p>
<p>I am in the rare position of getting to teach you leveraging tools which I and my team have built. This content is written in a platform called HAXcms which we are actively building. I'm also the project lead on a project called ELMS: Learning Network.</p>
<p>Since starting at Penn State, I would say 99.5% of every hour of every day I work is contributed directly back to open code and documentation. I've contributed hundreds of modules for Drupal, dozens of themes and installation profiles, millions of lines of code liberated from the ownership of anyone or anywhere.</p>
<p>In the last two years, our team has released north of 400 reusable design assets called Web components. These modules and design assets power thousands of websites and help empower people we'll never know to better express themselves online, whether for instructional content or otherwise.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/welcome/welcome/about-the-instructor</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:48:47 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Github</title>
      <link>/getting-started/github</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/getting-started/github</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:48:47 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Git</title>
      <link>/topics/git</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/topics/git</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:48:47 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Syllabus</title>
      <link>/syllabus</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>A standard looking syllabus but yet, a contract between us.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/syllabus</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:48:47 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Ocean</title>
      <link>/getting-started/digital-ocean</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/getting-started/digital-ocean</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:48:47 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accessibility</title>
      <link>/topics/accessibility</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/topics/accessibility</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:48:47 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Docker</title>
      <link>/topics/docker</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/topics/docker</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:48:47 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting started</title>
      <link>/getting-started</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/getting-started</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:48:47 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topics</title>
      <link>/topics</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/topics</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:48:47 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>/resources</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Ex uno Plures</p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/resources</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:48:47 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>/welcome</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>IST 402: Emerging Technologies</h2>
<grid-plate layout="8/4" responsive-size="md" style="width: 100%;"><p slot="col-1">This will hopefully be unlike any course you've taken before (in a good way). My name is Bryan Ollendyke, and welcome to IST 402!</p>


<p slot="col-1">I'm excited to expose you to the ideas I wish I had been exposed to when I was in IST. I graduated from IST in 2006 (and again in 2015).</p>


<meme-maker image-url="files/headshot.jpg" top-text="Your" bottom-text="Professor" imageurl="files/headshot.jpg" slot="col-2" style="width: 100%;"></meme-maker>


</grid-plate>
<h2>(Boring) BlueBook description</h2>
<h3>Start up? Let's Tool up!</h3>
<p>The "Start up" culture is a world that lives by "move fast and break things". But how do you get into the start up scene? Or more importantly, what do you need to know in order to attract offers, and get your resume to stand out in a world where thousands of "IT workers" will graduate along side you.</p>
<p>You'll contribute to a large Penn State lead Open Source software project while building your digital identity as an IT professional on your journey to 1337 (elite). You'll improve online education while using things like version control (git), docker, web components, terminal, servers, screencasting and writing technical documentation.</p>
<p class="hax-active">You'll work with platforms like Github, Digital Ocean, HAXcms, IFTTT, Slack, Travis CI and YouTube. Prior programming knowledge is beneficial but understanding of technical concepts is more important.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>/welcome</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 15:46:06 -0400</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>